Hi guys, today we're reviewing the AO
Pro. The It's a clone of the uh the Mi1
scooter. You see, it's almost identical.
Comes in about two/ird of the price. Um
but you can tell if you look around some
of the joints just how how much cheaper
sort of made it is. Um, some of the
other downside are the wires are a bit
more exposed
um and a bit more visible whereas in the
Miis they're a bit sort of more tucked
away and color coded. Um, the tires are
slightly different. They're slightly
bigger on the Mi. Um, but they've got
this honeycomb sort of latis design. Um,
it's a bit of a smoother ride the Miis.
Um, the Ever Pro is a bit a bit more
sort of shock shock filled. Um
the the the light is about three times
better on the on the Mi. Um and the
battery life is and the motor's a bit
bigger as well. Um so overall build
quality is not really there. So an AO
Pro is going to break a lot faster than
your Mi. Um
should we put it up?
Yeah, let's put it up. That's it. So
there we go. That's how you put it up.
I'll show that again. So there's a bit
of a latch there. You can just attach
the scooter. That allows you to carry it
like that. And to put it up, you just
kind of pull the latch up like that.
Clicks into place.
And then bang. That's it. Ready to ride.
And then again, show on the on the
Yeah. So So that latch is actually the
bell as well, isn't it?
Yeah. That latch
on the on the Pro. It's similar. So you
grab the latch, you pull it up. Um,
interestingly,
it's a bit more of a fiddly mechanism.
You sort of got to hold up the stem when
you're trying to click it into place,
and it's a bit tricky to click in place.
Um, and then the other thing to notice
is that latch isn't actually part of the
bell. It's got a separate um separate
bell. Some people might prefer that. I
think it makes this a bit pointless and
they probably should have made this a
bit a bit more solid. um UI on the on
the thing if you turn it on.
So UI on this is just battery speed and
tells you if it's in sport mode. So
there's sport mode. There's a light.
Just click it once. If you double click
it, you can go to walking mode. So we
show that. Yeah, that's walking mode.
That basically just if you hold the
button and push it, it basically takes a
the pain out of pushing. You can go to
drive mode, which is I believe just
economical
battery life. And then obviously sport,
which you saw at the start.
Yeah. And it's s similar over here. It's
got sport mode. Well, that's off. Uh
that's the light on. Double click it to
change mode. Um
one of the nice things about this one is
it accelerates straight away. So you can
can immediately accelerate. The the miis
you have to sort of get it up to a
certain speed.
5 miles an hour.
5 miles an hour. This
km an hour.
This one you just hit and it will go.
And there's a few strange features on
this which I'm sure you can turn off,
but if you get it to a certain speed and
you hold down the accelerator, it will
sort of lock in a speed which I find a
bit dangerous. The the Miis don't do
that. Um, and the bigger models don't.
And the good thing is when you break, so
when you pull that brake handle here,
when you pull that, if you look, I'm
pulling that now. The light at the back
automatically starts flashing.
So that's kind of good if you're driving
at night. It's the same on that as well.
That's a cool feature. So something to
note. One thing about the brakes on the
AO is they're a bit it's a bit sort of
front front heavy. So you'll find
yourself breaking sort of come back up.
The Miis are a lot smoother cuz it does
both a bit more equally. Um so so
overall the Mi lot smoother ride. Um and
obviously the build quality is a lot
better. I mean you can tell just from
the welds.
Battery wise. I mean we've not really
put that to the test yet but uh
speedwise they seem to be pretty
comparable. Battery wise, I'd say based
on the usage, I mean, we've drove about
the same amount of time. We both got
four bars, so it looks to be quite
similar.
I think the motor's definitely better on
the Mi going uphill. It definitely seems
like you can you can pull a bit more.
Um, so yeah, overall I think the I mean,
you get you get what you pay for. I
think the the AO Pro is going to break a
lot faster than the Mi. Um, I've heard a
lot of horror stories about picking up
by the stem and the stem snapping or
this back brake. Even though it's
reinforced snapping, you you don't get
out on the Mi just cuz the build quality
is so much better.
So, yeah. Uh, I think that's it for this
video. Uh, thanks for watching.
Subscribe and like. We're going to do
some more comparisons soon. But yeah,
thanks for watching