[Music]
hey thanks for watching guys and i'll
see you in the next one two thousand
years later guys i thought i'd give you
a quick recap of what we've been through
before i gave you the big reveal so
let's run that
[Music]
and things went from bad
to worse
to watch again
so as you can see straight off the bat
it's growing i'm going to get right
close as well and i'll give it a bit of
a second to focus in
as you can see it's getting really
really really thick uh hairs are
sprouting out everywhere
boom
this is what it's currently looking like
it's getting long it's getting bushy
some bits are longer than the others
yeah so i've just come in the shower and
my hair is still wet and this is what my
hair looks like wet
um
so yeah as you can see really fat really
full uh
yeah almost normal it's probably like
describe it yeah you can't really tell
it's a hair transplant done so yeah this
is what's currently looking like uh and
let me show you what else we drag so
i've just dried and styled here and this
is what kind of looks like day to day um
yeah i'm really happy with that super
flexible and it looks really natural in
my opinion and
yeah really happy with it have a bit of
a close-up uh
this is what it looks like when it's
long
hopefully you can see that
if i'm not i'll actually have my hair
sitting way shorter than this so i'm
going to go around and get my hair cut
and then i'll come back and show you
what it looks like when it's properly
done don't forget to like subscribe and
turn on notifications yet smash that
bell
drop a comment below let me know you're
there and let's get back to the video so
it's half past three and i've just had
my haircut a few games of people in the
barber shop and this is what i came away
with
um
yeah overall pretty chocolate uh it
looks good and this is what my hair is
currently looking like
i'll get up close so let's see it uh
there's nothing in my hair at the moment
apart from the hairspray
and yeah
so guys please like subscribe and all of
that stuff uh i'll be putting out a
video purely on the back of the hair
this one's been purely on the front and
we'll be doing that soon so stay tuned
for that and thanks for watching guys
[Music]
[Applause]
foreign