hey everyone welcome back to the channel
it's lewis fee and apologies i'm a
little bit later this week i've been
absolutely swamped
uh it will work so yeah let me jump
straight into the hair
and the recipient area
it's like so and
then the donor area as well let me turn
around
[Music]
so yeah that is the hair i am really
hoping to get a haircut soon but i don't
know how it's going to happen
because of lockdown but yeah i'm looking
to get this cut asap
but yeah overall happy with everything
and let me quickly jump outside and show
you what it looks like out there
so it's not the best lighting today to
be honest but yeah this is what the hair
is looking like
and natural light it's starting to get
quite long as well and
yeah so i'm going to leave it there for
this week but yeah thanks for watching
and i will be back on first day
at the normal time and i'll see you then