[Music]
hey guys
and welcome back to the channel it's
luis fe here and
firstly i want to apologize for not
uploading last week so
basically i've been doing a lot of
research into the latest advances of
hair technology and hair loss and i've
managed to crack
the code so as you can see on screen
this is all you need to do i'm only
kidding but how the
[ __ ] have they managed to get what 28
reviews and a lot of people probably
buying this so [ __ ] knows what's going
on in this world but actually no the
real reason was it's because my
girlfriend is chinese and last thursday
was chinese new year so i got roped into
celebrating that
uh so yeah i'm back last week and i'm
back
with the five month and the five month
update
so let's get into the hair and
boom this is what it's currently looking
like it's getting long it's getting
bushy some bits are longer than the
others it's
not the best i'm dying to get a haircut
and honestly i really wish i could but
it's just locked down
[ __ ] [ __ ] up at the moment but as
soon as i can get a haircut rest i'm
sure there will be but
in terms of the actual growth of the
transplanted area
uh it looks fantastic in my opinion um
yeah there's comparing to the video on
screen now
look how fun it looks like at that
moment in time i remember thinking
looking in the mirror and thinking [ __ ]
me list you need to do something about
this
boom we're five months and one week back
and
yeah as i said really looking fact
really looking full
and let me turn around and give it
the donor area
so five months in one week today outside
uh about one o'clock in the day you'll
see this later today but yeah this is
what my hair's looking like
right now a natural light thing anyway
let's jump into the monthly
side by side so we're gonna do week 16
no week 17 18 19 20
and you've just seen 21 so enjoy
[Music]
so i forgot to actually come with paul
last week so you've not got any footage
on that but
the day after chinese new year i went up
a hill
it was snowing pretty bad in scotland
and i managed to capture some footage of
what it looks like outside in the wind
so
roll that now
[Music]
also guys please do subscribe smash the
like button
all of that [ __ ] and please it really
helps me out comment as well
that helps me with algorithm even if you
just have to comment
i've commented for the youtube i'll give
them great help a lot so yeah
thanks for watching guys and i'll see
you in the next one
[Music]
you