A fundamental question in neuroscience
is why are biological brains so insanely
good at learning new things and
generalizing to novel conditions? At
least part of the answer seems to lie in
a theory of compositionality. Here is
what it means. Think about when you
first learn to ride a bicycle. Your
brain built a specific skill for
handling two wheels. Let's call it a
balancing module. Years later, you got
your driver's license and in the
process, you built a traffic rules
module. Now suppose you want to learn to
ride a motorcycle. To your brain, this
is a new task because it has never
encountered this specific behavior
before. But you don't start from
scratch. You take the balancing module
from the bicycle, snap it together with
the traffic rules module from the car,
and boom, you're riding the motorcycle.
The learning is incredibly quick. The
idea of compositionality states that the
brain treats skills kind of like Lego
bricks, building complex behaviors by
snapping together reusable components.
While this makes sense intuitively, how
can we prove that this kind of mixing
and matching happens physically at the
level of individual neurons? And where
in the brain is it happening? Today we
are exploring a paper by Tim Bushman's
group at Princeton which recently came
out in nature and set out to answer
this.
Before we dive in, a quick question. Out
of the last five papers you've read or
videos you watched, how much do you
actually remember? If you're like me,
you consume a ton of research content,
but most of it just evaporates.
If so, you're going to love our today's
sponsor, Recall. This is the next step
in personal knowledge management, an AI
supercharged second brain. Save content
with a browser extension and it becomes
a part of your knowledge base that you
can chat with, interconnect ideas
together, create new notes with an
integrated editor, and actually retain
everything through spaced repetition.
The newest feature launching is quiz
2.0, letting you fully customize the
type, complexity, and the number of
questions. As someone who believes
deeply in space repetition for
understanding complex topics, this is a
powerful approach to stay ahead of the
forgetting curve and build deeper
intuition. You can even share the
quizzes with others and compete on a
leaderboard. This is the rare tool that
I wish existed when I started my
learning journey. Try it for free at
getriall.ai
and use the code down in the description
for 25% off. Now, back to the video. The
authors looked at what happens in the
brain of a monkey when it plays a
special video game designed to probe
exactly this idea. It consisted of three
visual discrimination tasks. On every
trial, the monkey sees a morphed image
that has a certain shape on a spectrum
between a bunny and a tea and color
somewhere between red and green. In the
first [music] task, the monkeys had to
distinguish shapes. They had to move
their eyes to the upper left corner of
the screen if the image looked more like
a bunny and to the lower right if it
looked more like a T.
If the monkey got the answer right, it
received some juice as a [music] reward.
We'll call this task S1, which stands
for shape axis one. In the second task,
C2, the overall structure was similar,
but the monkey had to report the color
instead of shape and move its size along
a different axis, too. If the image is
more red than green, look top right.
Otherwise, look bottom left. Finally, in
the third task, C1, they had to report
the color, but move their eyes along
axis one. Look top left for green and
bottom right for red. Do you see the
beauty here? Task C1 is a composition.
It takes the sensory rule from C2 look
at color and the motor axis output from
S1 move along the top left bottom right
diagonal. If the brain is truly
efficient, it should not build a new
task C1 circuit completely from scratch.
It should say, "Ah, I will just grab the
color detector from C2 and wire [music]
it to the motor driver from S1." And
this is exactly what the author set out
to test
to get a glimpse of what is happening in
the brain. They implanted electrodes in
the prefrontal cortex, the area
responsible for higher order abstract
decisions, and recorded the activity of
hundreds of individual neurons as the
monkeys played the game. Because the
building block modules involve more than
one neuron, they couldn't just look at
the activity of single cells in
isolation. Instead, they needed a way to
describe what is happening in the entire
population of cells all at once. Imagine
a coordinate system where every axis
represents [music] the activity level of
a single neuron. If you record from a
100 neurons, you have a 100dimensional
space. At any given millisecond, the
state of the monkeykey's brain is a
single point in that space.
If we take brain activity from all the
trials when the monkey saw the red
category, we have a specific cloud of
points and trials with green images form
a different cloud. Now there might be a
specific direction in this neural
activity space that best separates the
two clouds. Mathematically this defines
a decision boundary that slices the
space into two halves, red and green.
We'll call this direction a color
subspace.
We can use that separating hyper plane
to build a classifier. It's a machine
that takes a previously unseen data
point in the activity space, checks
which side of the boundary it falls on
and hands you a prediction. It is a way
to decode the identity of the color
purely from neural activity. The
accuracy of this classifier is then used
to measure how much information there is
in the brain about the color variable.
The authors could successfully decode
the color identity from cortical
activity in both C1 and C2 tasks about
half a second after the image was shown.
This means that this information was
successfully processed and routed into
the prefrontal cortex forming the two
well-defined clouds in the activity
space. Importantly, however, when the
monkey was focusing on the shape in the
S1 task, the color could not be decoded.
This suggests that by the time image
processing reaches the prefrontal
cortex, this task irrelevant information
is actively thrown away. The red and
green clouds are all tangled up and
squashed together. Similarly, the shape
could be easily decoded during the S1
task, but not C1 or C2.
Now, here is the critical test. If we
think that building blocks are reused,
it means that the color subspace should
be the same in both tasks that rely on
color processing. The hyper plane inside
the classifier trained on task C2 should
be capable of separating red and green
clouds observed during task C1 and vice
versa. The accuracy of this kind of
cross task decoding should be high. And
this is exactly what they found. When
the researchers swap the decoders, they
still worked almost perfectly. In other
words, the color module in the brain is
physically reused between two different
tasks. Similarly, a classifier trained
to decode the movement direction
generalized well between S1 and C1
tasks, suggesting that the motor command
module is compositionally reused as
well.
So we have established that the brain
has a color module and a motor module
which exist as specific stable subspaces
in neural activity. But having the parts
isn't enough to actually solve the task.
The brain has to connect them
dynamically. In task C1, for example,
the brain needs to take the red signal
from the color subspace and route it to
the move bottom right signal in the
motor subspace.
The researchers visualized this by
tracking the neural activity within a
single trial. About 100 milliseconds
after the image appears, the neural
state jumps into the color subspace. But
then a few hundred milliseconds later,
[music] the state flows out of the color
subspace and rotates into the motor
subspace to guide the eyes.
Crucially, this flow depends on the
context. In task C1, the red vector
flows into axis one motor direction. In
task C2, that same red vector flows into
axis 2 motor direction. It acts exactly
like a railroad switch. The cargo, the
color is the same, but the task context
flips a junction that routes the train
down a different set of tracks to a
different destination. However, this
railroad switch only [music] explains
how we route the output. The brain also
faces a second problem. Selecting the
right input. Remember the monkey seen
both shape and color. In task C1, it
needs to route color and ignore shape.
In task S1, it needs to route shape and
ignore color. If the [music] brain gets
this one wrong, it sends the wrong cargo
down the track. So, who decides which
input to put on the train? To find out,
the researchers exploited a helpful
feature of the game, uncertainty. The
monkeys performed tasks in blocks. When
a new block started, the screen flashed,
but the monkey wasn't told which task
was next. They only knew along which
axis they had to move their eyes. If the
motor axis was two, it was simple
because only task C2 uses that axis.
However, when the break ended and the
monkeys had to perform a task along axis
one, they faced a mystery. Is the rule
color or shape? This created a perfect
experimental window. For the first few
dozen trials, the monkey had to guess,
learn from feedback, and slowly update
its internal belief about what the rule
was. The researchers trained another
decoder to read out this task belief
from neural activity. They found that
they could watch the monkeyy's
realization in real time, watching the
signal go from I think it's shape to,
oh, it's definitely color. And here's
the punch line. This abstract belief
signal physically reconfigured the
neural geometry. They found that task
belief acts as a gain knob on sensory
inputs. As the monkey realized he was in
the color task, the brain amplified the
color subspace, stretching the red and
green clouds further apart. and
simultaneously it suppressed the shape
subspace squashing the bunny and
T-clouds flat. This ensured that only
the relevant information was loud enough
to enter the routing switchboard.
So the mechanism of flexibility is
twofold. The brain builds reusable
orthogonal modules for every feature
like color shape and motor command and
then uses a central task belief signal
to adjust the gain on the inputs and set
the switches for the outputs.
Putting all together, this paper
provides evidence that the brain does
not relearn the world for every new
problem from scratch. Instead, it acts
as an engineer building a library of
fixed reusable components. When a new
challenge arises, the brain simply has
to engage relevant modules, compose them
together to route information through
the circuitry, and suppress irrelevant
ones. This explains why humans can adapt
to new environments so quickly. We're
not building new neural hardware from
scratch every time. Instead, we're just
wiring up our old existing Lego bricks
into a new configuration. If you enjoyed
the video, share it with a friends.
Subscribe to the channel if you haven't
already, and press the like button. Stay
tuned for more computational
neuroscience and machine learning topics
coming up.
>> [music]