so this is the front uh
i think it looks really good i run my
hands through it you can see how thick
it is how full it is and
yeah overall i think it's really really
good job the the tops not any less
effect than it was before still very
full and
this part here everybody says uh looks
great as well it's just the supposing of
the camera lights looks like different
floors in this bag but in person it
still looks really really good
uh
the hair line itself let me bring that
up it looks really natural i think it's
quite straight but not overly straight
so i'm happy with that as well really
brings out the facial features on the
back of the head could be better but
still happy