this video was brought to you by
Squarespace there is one Concept in
machine learning that nearly every
course in textbook starts with finding
the equation of a straight line that
best fits a scatter of
points the typical explanation goes
something like this we pick the line's
parameters to minimize the average
squared vertical distance from each
point but why vertical distances why
squares and not absolute values or some
other power where does that even come
from
you'll often hear justifications like
squares are easier to optimize or the
math just works out nicely Fair points
but to me that always felt somewhat
unsatisfying in this video I want to
share with you an alternative
perspective a probabilistic take on
linear regression that finally made
everything click for me it leads to the
same solution but offers a conceptual
shift that I found invaluable not only
does it answer those fundamental
questions it also connects the seemingly
simple problem to more complex topics
like generative modeling and parameter
regularizations in ways that might
surprise you let's Dive Right
[Music]
In let's first clarify what regression
actually means at its core it's about
uncovering a relationship between inputs
call them X and outputs y then using
that relationship to predict y for new
values of X unlike classification where
you are choosing between discrete
categories like yes and no regression
deals with continuous values a classic
example is predicting house price from
various features perhaps X1 is the
number of bedrooms X2 distance to the
subway Etc our task is to reconstruct
the price from these features at this
point most explanations jump directly to
minimizing squar errors in the line by
reducing those vertical gaps and yes
we'll get there but to truly understand
why this works let's step back and
reframe it through
probability let's treat our data as if
it emerges from a linear model plus some
noise imagine that somewhere in the
universe underlying source code the
ideal price of each house is given
precisely by a linear combination of
features weighted by some coefficients
for brevity let's Express this as the
dot product between weights and features
stacked into
vectors however real world data is messy
and it never perfectly follows the
linear patterns actual house prices are
influenced not just by those features we
collected but also by hidden variables
that we can't access Plus Market
fluctuations and human
behavior in other words our observed
values y are corrupted versions of those
ideal underlying values with noise term
Epsilon being added to them here Epsilon
represents everything we can't explain
with our features all the unknown
contributors to the price beyond our
control the critical Insight is that our
resulting regression equation depends on
our assumptions about this noise namely
Epsilon is shaped by countless tiny
inferences measurement errors untrack
variables random Market fluctuations all
added together when many small
independent effects accumulate
additively something remarkable happens
according to the central limit theorem
when you sum many independent random
variables regardless of their individual
distributions their sum approaches a
normal or gorion distribution The
Familiar B curve suppose we have a
candidate set of Weights W our
hypothesis about the underlying linear
model when we examine a random house
with features X and price y we can
calculate exactly how much noise was
added to our hypothesis by taking the
difference between the observed price Y
and its ideal non-noise value with our
noise model knowing that it follows a
caution distribution we can calculate
the probability of getting precisely the
right amount of noise Epsilon that would
push the underlying price to be
registered as y this equals the
probability of observing that particular
data point I want to reiterate that
shift of perspective with a working set
of Weights w we take the features X and
compute their weighted sum given us
where the ideal noiseless version of Y
should lie around this point exists a
cloud of uncertainty a bell curve
centered at w transpose X when we
observe the actual value of y and
calculate how much much noise must have
been added we can compute the likelihood
of that happening by plugging the noise
amplitude into the gor equation this
gives us the probability of observing a
single data point as the probability of
sampling just the right amount of noise
from the caution
distribution if we assume all data
points in our scatter plot were sampled
independently then the probability of
obtaining our entire data set with a
fixed w
can be found by multiplying the
probabilities of these independent
events what we have done is expressed
the probability of observing our data
given a particular model the
coefficients W if presented with two
alternative models intuitively the
better model would be the one with a
higher probability of generating The
observed data so when solving the
regression problem and choosing the
optimal w we just need to select the
configuration that maximizes this
probability given this optimization
objective we can expand the formula for
the probability of data now let's take
the logarithm of the right hand side
because logarithm is a monotonic
function whichever weight configuration
maximizes the total probability also
maximizes its logarithm the two
objectives are equivalent but the
logarithm transforms our product of
probabilities into a sum which is much
easier to work with
notice that Sigma the amplitude of the
underlying noise is a fixed value
determined by factors like Market
volatility from the perspective of the
optimization objective it is a constant
factor that doesn't affect which set of
Weights is optimal this allows us to
simplify the formula finally the
logarithm and the exponent cancel each
other out leaving us with this this is
exactly the well-known least squares of
objective which states that the optimal
coefficients should maximize the
negative or minimize the positive of the
sum of squared errors between the linear
fit and The observed points importantly
though we arrived at this from the
perspective of finding the linear model
that maximizes the probability of
observing our data and the square in the
resulting formula is a direct
consequence of assuming the Gau
noise this problem can be then solved
either through gradient descent by
making small iterative adjustments to
the weights or by directly jumping to
this solution using a closed form
expression found in any textbook my main
goal here was to show where this formula
comes from in the first
place just like linear regression helps
us find the optimal fit for the data
finding the right platform for your
online presence is all about making
smart choices which brings me to our
today's sponsor Squarespace Squarespace
transforms website creation and
management into a straightforward
process that anyone can Master while
starting a site from scratch might seem
challenging Squarespace design
intelligence feature makes it remarkably
simple this Innovative AI power tool kit
generates a website tailored to your
specific business in brand Vision filled
with relevant content and images from
this starting point you can enjoy total
creative freedom adjust all the visual
elements to match your style organize
content with their drag and drop tools
and even Implement ey catch in
animations to spice things up
importantly Squarespace goes beyond just
website building it's a comprehensive
digital solution where you can develop
online courses launch effective email
campaigns or set up payment processing
through various methods all within one
cohesive ecosystem experience it
yourself with a free trial at
squarespace.com and once you're ready to
launch visit squarespace.com AUM to save
10 % off your first purchase of a
website or
domain previously when choosing between
different sets of Weights w we always
pick the model with a higher probability
of generating The observed data the
lower means squared error but what if
two models have identical values for
that probability but differ in their
exact values for w would we have a
reason to prefer one over the
other if we know nothing about the
nature of of our features we have no
basis of comparing two equally
performing models but often we have
prior expectations about how features
might contribute to the predictions and
thus we have reasonable boundaries for
their values let's illustrate it with an
example suppose we have a coin with an
unknown bias where the probability of
heads is Theta between 0 and 1 we want
to estimate this value of theta by
tossing the coin and tracking the
results let's say we observe four hats
out of five tosses if we ignore any
assumptions about Theta and find the
value that maximizes the probability of
data we will conclude that Theta must be
0.8 indeed this type of biased coin
maximizes the probability of observing
four heads out of five tosses but
something doesn't seem right we know
from experience that most coins
typically land 50/50 maybe with a slight
bias due to a symmetry but certainly not
80 to
20 the problem is that our solution only
cared about maximizing the probability
of observed beta and completely ignored
prior beliefs about Theta which likely
is centered around 0.5 and decreases
towards the edges but is there a
systematic way to incorporate these
prior assumptions into our regression
objective instead of maximizing the
probability of data we can search for a
set of Weights W that maximizes the
joint probability of data and the
weights in other words we look for
weights that both explain the data well
and align with our prior beliefs about
what w should look like following the
conditional probability rule we can
decompose the total probability into the
following product the first factor is
the likelihood exactly what we had
before How likely a particular W is to
have generated our observed dat AA given
by the Cent formula for the noise the
second factor is the prior where we
incorporate assumptions about How likely
different values of w are the key idea
is that different assumptions on prior
distributions of Weights will lead to
different criteria how to choose between
alternative Solutions this shows up in
the overall objective as so called
regularization terms for the remainder
of the video I'd like to focus on two
most common types of regularization and
show how they are born from two common
priors one of the most popular choices
is to assume that weights W themselves
follow a zeroc centered caution
distribution why is that reasonable well
in regression each component of w is a
coefficient describing how a particular
feature in the X Vector like the size of
the house contributes to the prediction
y if we randomly select features
intuitively most will be probably
irrelevant with values near zero while
only a small subset will have
significant weights additionally since
each feature's coefficient in real data
is shaped by many underly unobserved
causes the central limit theorem applies
to the coefficients as well formally we
can write that the prior probability of
observing a particular set of Weights is
given by the product of probab ities of
individual components Each of which is
given by the Gan formula with some
variance
tow now going back to our optimization
objective we want to maximize The Joint
probability let's take the logarithm as
before and substitute our formulas for
the likelihood and the
prior flipping the signs and grouping
the two constants together we get the
following this is what's known as rid
regression or for L2 regularized linear
regression due to the square of the
weight
amplitudes the idea is that we are
searching for the model that would both
explain the data well but at the same
time be not overly complex where
complexity is measured as the sum of
squares of the weights this
regularization term penalizes large
weight values pushing them toward zero
exactly what we would expect from our
gion prior assumption notice how beauti
this emerges the parameter Lambda which
controls how strong the regularization
is is the ratio between the data noise
or the variance of the samples and the
variance of the prior distribution of
coefficients when we are very certain
about our prior Lambda becomes larger
given more weight to the regularization
term conversely when the data is very
reliable with small variance Lambda
decreases placing more emphasis on
fitting the data
but what if our intuition about the
weights is different instead of just
assuming they are generally small what
if we believe most should be exactly
zero with only a few significant ones
this would correspond to a model where
only a handful of features truly matter
favoring sparse
Solutions this assumption is
particularly relevant for biological
systems in genomics for example out of
thousand of genes only a small subset
typically influences a particular trait
similarly for Neuroscience only a small
sparse subset of all neurons are
responsible for encoding a particular
feature in this case a gan prior is not
ideal because it pushes weights towards
zero too gently instead we might prefer
a distribution with a sharp Peak at zero
which looks something like this this is
known as the LL distribution and it is
parametrized by symmetric exponentially
Fallen
tails the probability of the
configuration of W's as a whole can be
found by multiplying the probabilities
of each component and following the same
derivation as before taking the
logarithm to counteract the exponent our
optimization objective becomes the
following here Lambda is again the
combination of constance of noise
variance and the falloff of the weights
prior this is known as L1 regular
ization because the complexity penalizes
the absolute values of w rather than
their squares L1 regularization
typically leads to sparse Solutions
where many weights are exactly zero
which is preferable in many domains of
science all right let's tie everything
together today we explored the
probabilistic view of linear regression
and saw how the familiar least squares
equation naturally emerges when we find
the linear fit that maximizes the
probability of observing our data
importantly the squared error term
wasn't just an arbitrary Choice it is a
direct consequence of assuming caution
noise in our model while this assumption
is reasonable in most cases it may not
be appropriate in specific settings
where noise is correlated or
multiplicative in nature we've also seen
how incorporating prior beliefs about
the coefficients lead to different
regularization schemes providing a
principled approach to balancing models
accuracy with complexity the cion prior
gave us L2 regularization gently pushing
all weights toward zero while the llos
prior yielded L1 regularization favoring
sparse Solutions where most weights
become exactly zero this probabilistic
perspective extends far beyond linear
regression to nearly all machine
learning models
whether examining deep neural networks
as we saw in the previous video decision
trees or clustering algorithms viewing
them through the lens of probability
provides a much deeper understanding of
their underlying assumptions and design
choices if you like the video share it
with your friends subscribe to the
channel if you haven't already and press
the like button stay tuned for more
neuroscience and machine learning topics
coming up
[Music]