Your brain is constantly rewiring itself
with every single ongoing experience.
Like right now watching this video, the
physical connections between millions of
your neurons are being modified
dynamically. This incredible ability is
known as synaptic plasticity. And
figuring out the principles behind it is
one of the biggest goals in modern
neuroscience. Historically, this has
been notoriously hard to study. actually
seeing and measuring the strength of
these tiny synaptic connections is
experimentally even tougher than
recording the activities of neurons
themselves. But in recent decades,
thanks to some amazing advancements in
experimental methods, we are finally
getting a real glimpse into the world of
synaptic plasticity even in awake
behaving animals. And what we are
discovering isn't just some one
universal rule. Instead, it appears that
neurons have a whole toolkit of
different mechanisms they use in
different situations. As the study
published last month in the journal
science revealed and this is the paper I
would like to explore today, it appears
that the very same neuron actually uses
different plasticity rules for its
different signapses. So in this video we
will talk about what these different
plasticity mechanisms are, what methods
researchers used to uncover it and what
it might tell us about information
processing in cortical neurons.
Computation in our brain is carried out
by neurons which are electrically
excitable cells. This means that the
outer membrane of a nerve cell can
amplify and send waves of electrical
activity like brief zaps of charge
moving between the inside and outside
the cell. Typically, these electrical
signals are collected by thin branching
structures called dendrites. Think of
them as neurons receiving antennas. The
signals then travel towards the cell
body called the soma. Here a crucial
decision is made. If the incoming signal
is strong enough to cross a certain
threshold, the neuron fires off a large
electrical impulse called the action
potential. This action potential, often
just called a spike, then zips along the
axon, which is a specialized projection
acting as the neuron's outgoing wire.
But something really interesting happens
when this electrical signal needs to
jump from one cell to another. At the
point of contact called the sinapse, the
information completely changes its form.
Instead of staying electrical, it is
converted into chemical messengers.
These chemicals called neurotransmitters
are released by the sending neuron,
float across a tiny gap and when they
are detected by the receiving neuron,
they trigger new electrical signals
there. This electrical tochemical to
electrical conversion isn't just some
weird biological quirk. It is a super
sophisticated mechanism that allows for
the incredible flexibility and control
which make learning possible. When the
spike arrives at the end of a sending
axon, it kicks off a cascade of events.
First, this increased voltage at the
axon terminal causes special protein
channels to open, letting calcium ions
rush into the terminal. This flood of
calcium then causes tiny membranebound
sacks called vesicles which are packed
full of neurotransmitter molecules to
fuse with the cell membrane and spill
their contents into the synaptic clft
that tiny gap between the
neurons. When these molecules glutamate
being the most important for us today
bind to the receptor proteins on the
dendrite of the receiving neuron they
activate those
receptors. Now, most of these excitatory
sinapses are not located on the smooth
surface of the
dendrite. Instead, they are often found
on tiny mushroom-shaped protrusions
sticking out from the dendrite called
dendritic spines. Think of them as
little specialized compartments for
individual
sinapses. So, it is on these spines that
the glutamate binds to receptors
allowing ions to flow into the post
synaptic neuron and change its membrane
voltage. The strength of this sinapse,
basically how much the receiving neurons
voltage changes in response to the spike
of the center neuron depends on a lot of
different
factors. But for our purposes today,
let's think of the synaptic strength
mainly as the number of receptor
proteins embedded in the membrane of
that dendritic spine. So when plasticity
occurs, it would have to either grow
that spine and its sinapse, increasing
the surface area and adding additional
receptor proteins leading to stronger
signals, or shrink the spine and
sinapse, diminishing the effect of its
activation on the post synaptic membrane
voltage. When the strength of a sinapse
increases and stays that way for a
while, it's called long-term
potentiation or LTP.
Think of it as turning the volume up on
that specific connection. Now, I should
note that there is also short-term
potentiation, but this one is more
fleeting. It doesn't involve these
lasting structural changes. So, in this
video, we'll focus only on the long-term
kind, the one that truly rewires the
brain, lasting from hours to days. The
brain uses specific learning rules to
decide when to strengthen or weaken a
connection, often based on the activity
patterns of neurons involved. A famous
guiding principle attributed to the
psychologist Donald Hab is that neurons
that fire together wire together. The
idea is that if a sending neuron
consistently helps to make the receiving
neuron fire, the connection between them
should get stronger. This is a
cornerstone for understanding many forms
of LTP. The key question then becomes,
how does this tiny sinapse know when
it's time to change its strength? To
answer this, we need to zoom even more
into the molecular machinery inside the
sinapse. At the heart of these synaptic
changes lies a truly remarkable
molecule, the NMDA receptor. This
receptor can be thought of as a tiny
sophisticated coincidence detector
sitting right there at the
sinapse. Here is the general idea of how
it works. When the presinaptic neuron
spikes, it releases glutamate which
binds to a couple of main types of
receptors on the receiving neurons
dendrite. First, we have what's called
ampi receptors. These are like everyday
workh horses of signal transmission.
When glutamate latches onto them, they
quickly pop open and let positive sodium
ions rush into the receiving neuron.
This causes a small brief electrical
excitation, a little bit of
depolarization in that neuron. The
second kind is our special NMDA
receptors. When glutamate binds to these
receptors, they don't necessarily open
right away. This is because at the
neuron's resting state, the channel of
the NMDA receptor is physically blocked
by a magnesium ion. Imagine it like a
cork stuck in the neck of a bottle. Even
if glutamate is present and the channel
is open, other ions can't flow through
it because the magnesium is blocking the
entry. Now, you might be thinking, what
is the point of these NMDA receptors if
they are usually blocked anyway? Well,
here's where the magic happens. It turns
out that if the membrane of the
receiving neuron becomes deolarized
enough, meaning it gets sufficiently
positively charged, right where NMDA
receptor is located, this positive
charge can actually push the magnesium
out of the channel. With the cork gone,
the NMDA receptor can finally open wide
and let the calcium ions in. Calcium is
an incredibly versatile messenger
molecule inside the cell. When it floods
through an open NMDA receptor, it
initiates the whole cascade of different
molecular events. These ultimately
signal the neuron to do things like
insert more receptors into the membrane
of the sinapse and even reorganize the
cell's internal scaffolding, the actin
cytokeleton, which can make the
dendritic spine physically larger.
So when a significant amount of calcium
enters through these NMDA receptors, it
is essentially the neuron getting the
message. This particular signapse was
with a strong activation of the neuron.
So let's crank it
up. But what causes this crucial
deolarization which expels the magnesium
block in the first place? Won't sodium
coming in through the open amper
receptors automatically do the trick?
Well, here is where it gets interesting.
Usually the activation of amper
receptors at a single sinapse on its own
causes deolarization that is too small
and too brief to reliably open NMDA
receptors. This is where the coincidence
detector part truly shines. For
significant NMDA receptor activation and
that vital calcium influx, we generally
need a stronger and more sustained
deolarization. This can happen in a
couple of main ways. First leading to
classical headband plasticity is the
effect of the post synaptic neuron
actually firing its own spike. If the
receiving neuron gets enough excitatory
input from many different sinapses all
summing up from different dendrites, its
entire cell body might depolarize enough
to fire its own action
potential. Now that spike doesn't just
travel down the axon to signal the next
neuron. an echo of it can also spread
backwards into the
dendrites. We call this a back
propagating action potential. As a quick
note, despite the name similarity, this
is totally different from back
propagation in machine learning setting
which is about how artificial neural
networks learn. Here a back propagating
action potential is just a wave of
depolarization traveling in reverse
direction from the cell body back into
the dendrites of the same neuron. it
doesn't communicate anything to other
neurons only to the sinapses of that
neuron signaling that it just
spiked. So if a presinaptic neuron
releases glutamate and this glutamate is
still present bound to the NMD receptors
when the back propagating action
potential sweeps through that part of
the dendrite the conditions for
long-term potentiation can be met. The
glutamate ensures that the NMDA receptor
is primed and the strong deolarization
from the back propagating spike then
provides the necessary voltage kick to
expel the magnesium block. This near
simultaneous presence of glutamate and
strong depolarization allows calcium to
flood in triggering the strengthening
pathways.
It's this crucial pairing, the
presinaptic activity preceding or
coinciding with the post synaptic spike
that embodies the fire together wire
together principle for this kind of
plasticity. But there is another way
this can happen leading to what's called
non-hibane plasticity. Neurons
especially parameal cells we find in the
cortex have these incredibly complex
branching dendrites. Now imagine if
several sinapses that are very close to
each other on one of these fine
dendritic branches all become active
around the same time. Their individual
amp mediated deolarizations can add up
locally right there in this tiny segment
of the dendrite. If this local sum is
strong enough, it can push out those
magnesium blocks from the NMDA receptors
in that specific neighborhood, even if
the neuron as a whole doesn't fire an
action potential. This allows for highly
specific compartmentalized
plasticity. Through this kind of local
coactivity, the neuron can strengthen a
little cluster of inputs on one
dendritic branch independently of what
the rest of the neuron is
doing. Great. Now we understand
precisely the question that the science
paper was addressing. When a signapse
under goes plasticity, one determines
whether it's the heben mechanism driven
by that post synaptic spike coinciding
with the input or does it happen through
the non-heb local coactivity instead?
And crucially is there any pattern to
this? Do certain kinds of synapses
prefer one mechanism over the other? To
find out, let's dive deeper into what
exactly the researchers
did. They focused their attention on
parameal cells in the motor cortex of
mice. These are the key neurons involved
when we learn new movements. Parameal
neurons have a very characteristic shape
with a main thick trunk-like dendrite
called the aical dendrite. This epical
dendrite reaches up towards the surface
of the cortex and then branches out
extensively like a crown of a tree.
Closer to the cell body, there is also a
bushier set of basil dendrites that
spread out more horizontally. These
different dendritic compartments, a
versus basil, don't just look different.
They also receive inputs from different
sources and have distinct electrical
properties. The authors hypothesized
that these distinct dendritic
compartments might actually employ
different plasticity rules.
Specifically, they suspected that the
plasticity in the basal dendrites which
are electrically closer to the cell body
where action potentials are usually
generated might be more reliant on the
classical hairband mechanism. The
coincidence of synaptic input and the
neurons own back propagating action
potentials. But for a dendrites,
especially those fine distant branches,
they thought a different non-hebian rule
might apply. Perhaps because these
regions are so far away from the soma
and more electrically isolated,
plasticity there is driven more by local
coactivity between nearby sinapses on
the same dendritic branch independently
of the cell body.
While previous work in brain slices
demonstrated these kind of compartment
specific rules, it was still a big open
question whether those processes
actually happen this way in the brain of
an alive animal that is actively
learning something new. And this is
exactly what they set out to
test. To study plasticity in a natural
learning setting, the researchers
trained mice on a motor task. Animals
had to learn to press a lever beyond a
certain point in response to an auditor
cue to get a sugary reward. As mice got
better at this task over several days,
pressing more successfully and with
quicker reaction times, their motor
cortex was busy rewiring itself through
synaptic plasticity. Now, during this
learning process, the group was
monitoring what was happening inside the
mouse brain. If you just look at the
brain under a normal microscope, you
won't be able to see these subtle
synaptic changes. So they had to employ
some very clever tricks using advanced
imaging methods. First, to actually see
the synaptic input, they genetically
modified the neurons to express a
special protein, a glutamate sensitive
fluorescent reporter, which is
colloquially pronounced as glue sniffer.
This sensor sits at the sinapse and
lights up when it binds to
glutamate. This allowed them to see the
activation of individual sinapses in
real time as flashes of green
light. At the same time, to monitor the
neuron's own activity, they used another
fluorescent protein, a red glowing
calcium indicator called
RCAMP. Calcium levels shoot up inside
the neuron when it's active. The
researchers established that large
widespread calcium signals that flooded
entire segments of image dendrites were
a reliable proxy for the neuron firing a
spike. This was crucial because it
allowed them to identify moments of
heavy coincidence when a sinapse got
input right around the time when the
whole neuron fired.
Finally, the authors also took
structural images of the same exact
dendritic spines over consecutive days
before and after the learning sessions.
By precisely quantifying how the size of
each individual sinapse changed from one
day to the next, they could identify
which sinapses had undergone LTP as
detected by the spine getting bigger.
So with this impressive setup, they
could correlate the activity patterns of
individual synapses and the whole neuron
on one day with the physical changes in
those sinapses on the next. This allowed
them to directly ask what kind of
activity predicts whether a sinapse will
get stronger during learning. And what
they found was pretty remarkable,
beautifully confirming the hypothesis.
The rules for synaptic plasticity were
indeed strikingly different depending on
whether they were looking at the epical
or basal dendrites of the very same
neuron. When they analyzed the synapses
on aical dendrites, they discovered that
their strengthening as seen by the spine
growth was best predicted by local
synaptic coactivity. In other words, an
epical spine was much more likely to
grow if it and its immediate neighboring
spines on the same branch were
frequently active together during the
learning session on the previous day.
Interestingly, whether or not the whole
neuron fired in action potential at the
same time did not seem to be the primary
driver for plasticity. It was all about
that local neighborhood coactivity. To
really nail this down, the authors
performed a crucial experiment. They
used a genetic tool to specifically
block the neuron from firing action
potentials. Even when the postsaptic
neuron could not spike, plasticity in
aical dendrites was largely
unaffected. This was powerful evidence
showing that a dendrites indeed use a
non-habin spike independent mechanism
for plasticity.
But when they shifted their focus to
basal dendrites, the story changed
completely. Here the strengthening of
synapses was best predicted by the
classical heben mechanism. The
coincidence of synaptic input and the
neurons own action potentials. This
suggests that the functional clustering
of synapses might be a less prominent
feature for basal dendrites compared to
aical ones.
And just as they did previously, when
the researchers blocked the neuron from
firing action potentials, the ability of
these basil sinapses to undergo LTP was
significantly
diminished. So the evidence was
incredibly clear. The same neuron was
using two distinct plasticity rules in
its different dendritic compartments.
Epical sinapses seem to prioritize local
teamwork and could modify themselves
based on patterns of input within their
small neighborhood. Basil sinapses on
the other hand were more tuned to
whether their activity contributed to
the overall output of the
neuron. But why might such functional
diversity within a single neuron be
important? Isn't it just a consequence
of the way neurons are shaped and their
electrical properties? for example that
the distal apical branches are
electrically isolated and so the back
propagating action potentials just don't
effectively invade them. Well, that's
certainly a part of the picture.
However, the difference between a and
basal dendrites goes beyond basic
biohysics. These compartments are wired
up to receive different kinds of
information. For example, a dendrites
are known to receive so-called feedback
connections. Those are signals sent from
higher order cortical areas back to the
lower level processing regions often
carrying contextual information or if
you've watched my previous video on
predictive coding they might carry the
brain's predictions about upcoming
sensory input. In contrast basal
dendrites typically receive feed forward
inputs. This is information flowing in
the other direction along the processing
hierarchy carrying the results of
earlier computations.
In the context of predictive coding,
basal dendrites are prime locations for
receiving prediction errors. Mismatch
between what was predicted and what was
actually observed. In fact, there is a
whole very fascinating line of research
which we might explore in future videos
suggesting that the very anatomy of the
parameal neuron with two distinct input
zones might be the way of the brain
physically implement the computation for
comparing predictions and reality. At
this stage, however, we don't have a
definitive answer for why learning rules
need to be different in these
compartments. Perhaps the non-hib and
local co-activity at the aical branches
is particularly useful for binding
together different patterns of
contextual input, allowing the neuron to
learn complex associations. Meanwhile,
the hein mechanisms at basal dendrites
might be crucial for strengthening the
pathways that reliably drive the neuron
to fire, effectively wiring different
cells into specialized computational
circuits. But one thing is crystal clear
from studies like this. We keep
uncovering evidence that biological
neurons are vastly more complex and
sophisticated information processing
devices than we previously thought. Such
insights are still largely waiting to
make their way into the field of
artificial intelligence. But perhaps
this kind of clever compartmentalized
learning using different rules for
different components will turn out to be
one of the keys to understanding the
brain's incredible computational
capabilities and efficiency. In the
meantime, if you're interested in
exploring deeper how computation can be
carried out by single neurons, check out
our today's sponsor, brilliant.org.
Brilliant is one of the best places to
master STEM topics online. They offer a
wide range of engaging courses combining
interactive visualizations with hands-on
problem solving. This approach allows
you to learn by doing and develop
intuitive understanding in byite-size
lessons. Especially relevant to today's
topics is their new course on digital
circuits which covers the fundamentals
of computation from logic gates which
are ubiquitous in neuroscience and
engineering to truth tables and
equivalent circuits. Brilliant also
offers a huge collection of other
courses in math programming and related
fields. Whether you're just starting out
or looking to expand your knowledge into
new frontiers, Brilliant has something
for everyone. If you're ready to embrace
your curiosity, head to
brilliant.org/ardam kursenov to get a
30-day free trial of everything
Brilliant has to offer, plus a 20%
discount on annual membership. If you
enjoyed the video, share it with your
friends, subscribe to the channel if you
haven't already, and press like button.
Stay tuned for more neuroscience and
machine learning topics coming up.
[Music]