This is neocortex, a sheet of cells just
a few millimeters thick covering the
surface of the brain. It is the most
recent addition in our evolutionary
history. And it's the structure
responsible for nearly everything we
consider uniquely human from language to
abstract reasoning. For decades,
scientists have tried to reverse
engineer this remarkable tissue. But a
deep mystery has always remained. What
are the unifying principles governing
the coordinated dance of billions of
cortical neurons?
In recent years, a powerful new
framework has emerged. The thousand
brains theory pioneered by Jeff Hawings
and the team at Nenta proposes a single
elegant explanation for what the
neoortex does and how it works. In this
video, we're going to dive deep into
this theory and explore the intricate
biological machinery behind what might
be the fundamental building block of
intelligence, the cortical column.
For over a century, since the pioneering
work of Rammonica Hall, autonomists have
known that the entire cortical sheet
shares a common blueprint. No matter
where you look, the basic circuitry and
cell types arranged into six
characteristic layers appear to be the
same.
The next turning point came from the
work of neurohysiologist Vernon MCastle
who revealed how this anatomy translates
into a stunningly consistent function.
Using microelerodes to listen to neural
activity, he discovered a key principle.
As he lowered the electrode straight
down through the cortical layers, he
found that all the cells in the vertical
column about half a millimeter wide were
all doing the same job. in the somata
sensory cortex. He discovered all the
cells in a column responded to a
stimulation on the exact same patch of
skin.
Soon after David Hubil and Torstston
Weasel famously confirmed this columnar
principle in a completely different
system, the visual cortex. There they
found columns of cells that were all
tuned to respond to a line of the exact
same orientation.
So the evidence was overwhelming. The
neo cortex is not a collection of many
unique structures. It is built from a
single type of processing module. The
six layer column replicated over and
over again. This led to the columnar
hypothesis. If the functional hardware
is universal, then the fundamental
computation, the algorithm it performs
must be universal as well. Seeing,
hearing, language, and abstract thought
might all be different manifestations of
the same underlying neural process. The
only thing that changes is the data
being fed into the columns as input.
This reframes our entire quest to
understand the neoortex. Perhaps we
don't need to find hundreds of different
solutions for all sorts of different
problems. We just need to find one
universal algorithm that powers each of
these information processing units. And
this kind of canonical computation is
exactly what the thousand brains theory
aims to describe.
Many modern theories of brain function
converge on a single powerful idea that
the fundamental purpose of neural
computation is to build a predictive
model of the world. This internal model
allows us to understand the present,
plan the future, and navigate
uncertainty. all to increase our chances
of survival. If you're interested in
this, I covered related frameworks like
predictive coding and the free energy
principle in previous videos.
The thousand brains theory takes this
concept and adds an important twist. It
proposes that the brain doesn't build
one single monolithic model of the
world. Instead, every single cortical
column is its own complete modeling
system. Think of it this way. Rather
than being one giant centralized
factory, the cortex is like 150,000
parallel minifactories.
Each one learns its own complete model
of things from simple lines to complex
objects. Your singular rich perception
of the world is the result of these
thousands of mini brains constantly
comparing notes and voting to reach a
consensus.
This elegant idea immediately solves a
major evolutionary puzzle. How did the
human brain become so powerful so
quickly? Evolution did not have to
invent hundreds of new brain components
specialized to different cognitive
functions and later figure out how to
wire them all together properly.
Instead, it had to do something much
simpler. Add more columns. Adding more
instances of the same universal module
vastly increase the brain's
computational power. You're not adding
fundamentally new kinds of machinery.
You're simply expanding the pool of
voters which leads to a more detailed
and robust model of the world. So how
does one minifactory a single cortical
column actually work? The core idea
revolves around learning the structure
of things through sensory motor
coupling. To understand it, let's begin
with a simple analogy.
Imagine you're in a pitch black room
with a statue that you can't see. And
your goal is to understand what that
object is. simply by touching it. If you
only focus on this sensation from your
fingertip, you will get a sequence of
disconnected feelings like smooth cold
marble, then sharp metallic edge
followed by rough carved stone. You will
have a list of features, but no real
understanding of the statue itself. The
key is to also track your own movement.
Let's say you start at the statue's
foot, but you don't know it. Your brain
registers the sensation rough stone and
anchors it to some starting position on
your mental map. Let's call it 0 0. Then
you move your hand up 1 meter. Your
brain receives a copy of this motor
command and updates your position on the
map to something like 010.
At this new location, you feel smooth
marble. You've just done something
really important. Binding a sensation to
a location derived from movement.
You continue this process, move, update
location, sense, and add the new feature
to your map. After exploring for a
while, you no longer have a simple list
of features. You now have a rich
structural model where features are
anchored to specific locations.
This map is what the theory calls a
reference frame.
Once a column has this map, it gains
this superpower of prediction. By
knowing its current location on the
statue, it can predict what it would
feel if it moves to a new spot.
This process of tracking your location
based on a sequence of movements is a
known neural computation called path
integration. It's how you can navigate
in the dark and find your way back to
where you started.
This brings us to a profound application
of the theory. For this process to work,
every single column must have its own
sensory motor system. While it's obvious
for columns in the motor cortex, the
theory makes a bold prediction, every
other column also has a motor output.
But what motor means can change. In the
visual cortex, for example, columns send
commands to muscles that move your eyes.
And in the brain's more abstract areas,
a motor command might be simply an
instruction to shift your attention or
recall a specific memory.
So the universal algorithm is this
constant sensory motor loop which
carries out the binding of sensory
inputs and locations.
Great. Now let's see how this process is
physically implemented in the six cell
layers of a real cortical column.
To understand the origins of the
cortical column, it's helpful to step
back in evolutionary time. Long before
the advent of the six layered neoortex,
our ancestors faced the fundamental
challenge of navigating the world,
memorizing locations of food and
shelter, and planning efficient routes.
This complex job is handled by the
specialized set of structures deep in
the brain called the hippocample
formation. At a high level, it has three
main components that work in tandem. the
medial and lateral parts of the entrinal
cortex and the hippocampus itself. Now,
because these structures are
evolutionarily older, their architecture
is different. The hippocampus is an
example of what's called alo cortex,
which is composed of only three layers.
And the entrinal cortex is an
evolutionary bridge between the ancient
alo cortex and the modern neoortex. It
also has six layers, but its internal
wiring is different. It doesn't have the
same columnar structure. In broad
strokes, hippocample formation works as
follows. The medial portion of the
entrinal cortex encodes pure location
information.
It contains famous grid cells, neurons
which act as a universal coordinate
system, firing in a hexagonal grid as
the animal moves, constantly tracking
its location.
But a map is useless without landmarks.
The sensory what signal sights sounds
smells is encoded in the lateral
entrinal cortex. These two information
streams what and where from both
divisions are then sent as the input to
the hippocampus.
This is where the crucial binding takes
place. Parameal neurons in the
hippocampus called play cells fire
encoding a location in a specific
context. This is why while a grid cell's
firing pattern is mostly fixed, response
properties of place cells completely
change if you alter the sensory features
of the environment. A phenomenon called
remapping. If you're interested in more
detail on hippocample formation, we
covered place and grid cells in earlier
videos. Now, here is the stunning twist
of today's story. The thousand brains
theory proposes that this exact
principle binding a what signal and a
where signal to form a specific model is
the universal algorithm of the cortex.
The brain essentially took the entire
modeling toolkit from the hypocample
formation, miniaturized it and copied it
into every single cortical column. So
let's follow that blueprint. Let's
examine the six layer architecture of
the neoortex and try to locate where the
analogs of this ancient circuitry ended
up.
The most straightforward component to
locate is layer 4. This is the column's
primary input port receiving sensory
data from the phalamus. When you see a
specific edge or feel a particular
texture, it's neurons in layer 4 that
fire first. This is the what signal
making layer 4 the direct analog of the
lateral entrinal cortex. Next we need to
find the analog of the medial part. The
division which generates the wear
signal. This crucial job of location
tracking is thought to belong to layer
6.
One of the key predictions of the
thousand brains theory is that every
column contains its own set of grid
cell-like neurons in layer 6. These
neurons form a coordinate system
tracking the location of the column's
associated sensor, whether it's the
position of the finger, the direction of
our gaze, or even an abstract cognitive
variable. And indeed, there is a growing
body of evidence showing these grid
cell-like properties throughout the
cortex.
But for these grid cells to work, they
need to know how the sensor is moving.
This brings us to layer five, the
column's primary action output.
When a layer 5 neuron fires to generate
a motor command like move the eye along
with sending that command to aector
muscles, it also sends an copy, an
internal carbon copy of that command to
its neighbors in layer 6 within the same
column. The cells in layer 6 then use
this movement information to perform
path integration and update the column's
current location on the map. So we found
our inputs what from layer 4 and where
from layer 6 calculated by motor
commands of layer 5. Now we need to bind
the two together. This is the job of the
upper layers 2 three of the cortical
column which makes it a loose analog of
the hippocampus.
These layers receive both the sensory
input from below and the location
context from deeper layers. Technically,
the location information is not sent
directly up the column. Instead, neurons
in layer 6 communicate with upper layers
via phalamus, broadcasting positional
information. A layer 23 neuron then
learns to represent complete objects by
binding sensory features with location.
This is where the stable predictive
model is formed.
Finally, there is layer 1, the very top
layer. It contains very few neurons and
is mostly composed of neural wiring,
dendrites and accents of neurons whose
cell bodies are located in other layers.
This is where the location signal from
layer 6 arrives priming the dendrites of
the neurons below and setting up the
columns predictions.
And with that we have the complete
circuit. A beautiful self-contained
modeling machine. Each column uses a
sensory moral loop to build predictive
models by binding sensory features to
locations on the map. And what the
column actually does, whether it's
feeling a coffee cup or solving a math
problem, simply depends on the type of
information arriving at layer 4 and the
kind of sensor, physical or abstract,
that the column controls.
But if each column acts as its own mini
brain, how do we perceive the world as a
single unified hole? This brings us to
the crucial idea of voting.
Imagine you're grasping a coffee cup in
the dark. Your fingers all project two
different sets of columns in your brain.
Your thumb touches the handle, so its
columns sense a C-shaped ceramic object.
Your index finger is on the rim. So its
columns sense a circular edge in each
column. The neurons in layer 2 three
represent possible explanations for the
sensation. But a single sensation is
ambiguous. The circular edge felt by
your index finger could belong to a
coffee cup or a saucer or a wine glass.
As a result, multiple sets of neurons,
each representing a different object,
become partially active. The column is
holding several hypothesis at once.
The columns of the thumb face the same
problem. Their C-shaped sensation is
consistent with the coffee cup handle, a
teapot spout, or even a cabinet drawer,
causing several groups of neurons in
layer 2 three to become partially
active. Notice the crucial point of
overlap. The coffee cup is the only
hypothesis that appears on both lists.
It is the only object consistent with
both the C-shaped handle and a circular
rim in their correct locations. The
thousand brains theory proposes that
columns agree on this shared hypothesis
through a rapid process of voting. This
reveals a key architectural feature.
Each column has two distinct outputs.
The first from layer 5 sends motor
commands to act on the world. As we saw
previously, the second from layer 2
three sends signals sideways to other
columns. Its purpose is not to move a
muscle but to reach a consensus by
refining predictions and resolving
ambiguity. Here is roughly how the
voting process unfolds.
In the first milliseconds after you
place your fingers on the cup, the
network is a noisy chatter of
conflicting hypothesis. But very quickly
the neurons in layer 2 three in
different columns begin to vote.
Consider the coffee cup neurons in your
index finger column. They receive
convergent evidence, the bottomup
sensory data for a circular rim and
supporting votes from the coffee cup
neurons in your thumb column. This
reinforces the coffee cup hypothesis by
driving those neurons to fire more
strongly. Meanwhile, the wine glass
neurons are in trouble. They have local
sensory evidence, but they receive no
supporting votes from the thumb column.
Lacking this reinforcement, their
activation fades, and they're suppressed
by the strong activation of their coffee
cup neighbors.
This creates a kind of rich get-richer
cascade. As the coffee cup neurons fire
more strongly, they send out more
powerful votes, which further reinforces
the coffee cup neurons in other columns.
The result is a rapid convergence. In a
fraction of a second, the one hypothesis
that is mutually consistent across the
network amplifies itself into a stable
unified consensus. All competing
inconsistent hypotheses are silenced and
your brain arrives at a single unified
perception.
So far, we've used concrete examples
like touching a statue or holding a
coffee cup. But the real power of the
thousand brains theory lies in how it
scales from physical motion to higher
more abstract forms of human thought.
The theory makes a beautiful and simple
proposal that the underlying algorithm
is identical. It's just using a
different kind of sensor and a different
kind of movement.
The input arriving at columns layer 4
doesn't have to come from our skin or
eyes. It can come from the layer 2 three
output of other columns. In this view,
the stable perception of a coffee cup
from a lower level column can become the
sensory input to a column higher in the
cortical hierarchy. And what is the
motor command? Well, instead of moving a
finger, this higher level column issues
a command to shift the attention
directing which sets of lower level
columns provide the next piece of input.
Imagine tackling a complex logical
problem. You are in essence navigating a
conceptual space. Each step, like
recalling a fact, applying a rule, or
focusing on a sub problem, is a mental
move that takes you to a new location in
the problem's abstract terrain. As you
trace this journey, guided by rules
learned from past experience, your
cortical columns are executing the very
same algorithm they use when exploring a
statue in the dark. This offers a
compelling and unified view of the
neoortex, a vast network of thousands of
mini brains, each learning a predictive
model of its surroundings by binding
sensations to locations on a reference
frame derived from movement. Of course,
this theory is still a work in progress,
and many aspects of brain function don't
fit so neatly into this picture, but it
is an important first step, and it
provides a powerful conceptual framework
of thinking about intelligence in a new
way. One that brings together anatomy,
physiology, and behavior under a single
unifying umbrella. A central theme of
our discussion today is that learning is
not a passive process. The brain builds
its powerful models not just by seeing,
but by doing, by moving, interacting,
and actively exploring the problem. This
philosophy of active learning is exactly
why I'm excited to tell you about our
sponsor, brilliant.org.
Brilliant is an innovative platform
designed to be uniquely effective way to
learn. They help you become a better
thinker and problem solver through
bite-sized, engaging lessons in STEM
fields. What makes Brilliant so powerful
is their focus on hands-on experience.
Rather than just passively reading or
watching a lecture, you get to learn by
doing, exploring interactive diagrams,
and practicing real world problem
solving. I'm a big fan of this approach
because Brilliant builds complex ideas
up from first principles and helps you
develop an intuitive understanding of
complex topics.
They have an incredible library of
courses crafted by an award-winning team
from places like MIT, Cartek, and
Google. So whether you want to
strengthen your math fundamentals or
dive into advanced topics like neural
networks, Brilliant is a phenomenal way
to embrace your curiosity. To get
started, head to brilliant.org/artaminov
to claim your 30-day free trial of
everything they have to offer, plus a
20% discount on annual subscription.
If you enjoyed the video, share it with
your friends, subscribe to the channel
if you haven't already, and press like
button. Stay tuned for more neuroscience
and machine learning topics coming up.
[Music]